[Music]
he
hello and welcome back to the ask abijit
show I hope you're all doing fantastic
you're all doing great today is episode
192 and I'm going to take a bunch of
questions from you about various matters
of Interest so as always let's see who
all is on the live chat I can see
Lucifer sinik Hill
FFG shagun Chopra Vishnu mohanan T ARA
chakrabarti
Lou vaka kabila Raa ainash Omar Sonu
Prashant har agal AR clash with pushkar
so am ra Zub zubon Isen s Loi somi jit
mukarji har Agarwal thre Ripper Matrix J
Jang thean pramesh anant Pai red endan
Shri ramachandra namaha sesma niharika
Gupta Lucifer again Tushar akarat
Vladimir hello Aman Singh Rohit jangid
bianda Panda suryakant dager
geopolitical du Anand P astral harp
Vishnu mohanan ragir solanki Sujin B
Jang Daman
AR Anand mahes dollar dollar nain Kumar
samit ml bird
num Pand you've seen the movie haven't
you um Vladimir space KGB agent anit
Shing kamat estal harp and everybody
else welcome to the live the live stream
I really appreciate you being here anjit
troll from Nepal
hello uh Kunal ishwara samud Ranjit
history ex mythology Anand Chandra
sharan gaming lover OAS Miguel Dias hi
insanely boy and everybody else Shivani
himansu chirag Tushar everybody else
thank you thank you so much for being on
the live stream so I'm going to take a
bunch of questions from that you've
asked in the comments and after that
I'll take a number of questions from the
live chat itself so let us begin with
question number one what is question
number one what do we have today let's
see
it's by Surendra Gupta is the Petro
Dollar Deal between Saudi Arabia and the
United States over what are the
implications yes so the news came out
recently about a week ago or so that the
uh Petro dollar deal that the Saudi
Arabia that Saudi Arabia had signed with
the US is now officially over the Saudis
have chosen not to uh revive or continue
that agreement and this agreement was
signed uh in 1974 for the first time and
what was the agreement the Petr dollar
agreement the agreement was that Saudi
Arabia would sell uh its petroleum
only with the US dollar as the currency
it would only accept US dollars when
when it would sell petroleum so this
made the US dollar it it entrenched the
US dollar and and solidified the US
Dollar's position as the world's Reserve
currency and the main currency or only
currency in which you could trade in in
petroleum so that is something that
allowed the US to establish its to
establish its Primacy its Supremacy and
so on worldwide in the 20th century and
now this is over so the implications are
that first of all what's what does it
mean that this deal is over and and in
exchange for the Saudis uh agreeing to U
use the US dollar only as a currency the
Americans gave them a lot of economic
benefits military aid U all Saudi
Arabian Army weapons
military weapons are us uh weapons us
made weapons and so on so the Saudis
became a loyal let's say Ally of the US
and they got lots of benefits in
exchange for making the US dollar the
only currency in which they would trade
in oil so that was a deal now that deal
is over so what does that mean it means
the Saudis will now uh
sell petroleum
oil and they will accept other
currencies apart from the US dollar as
well so what currencies uh could these
be it will it could be the ruble the
Russian Ruble the Chinese Yuan the Euro
possibly the Indian rupee even even
currencies like Bitcoin Etc could be
could be accepted by the Saudis uh so
that is what it means that's the
immediate implications of that and that
obviously diminishes the value of the US
dollar internationally doesn't isn't it
so does it mean that uh the US dollar is
doomed and uh doesn't mean that the US
Dollar's value will fall will it
depreciate what what could happen and
why is the US seemingly okay with this I
mean the US is the world's preeminent
power is the sole superpower it has
destroyed entire nations for Less so why
is it okay with the Saudis are going
ahead with ending the Petro dollar
agreement
um I I get the feeling that this could
be part of a script there is a script it
seems like to me that is being played
out right now and this could have
something to do with technological
advancements uh the rise of artificial
intelligence AI the rise of Technologies
like the like like blockchain The
blockchain Ledger all
that you know when certain momentous
changes happen to technologically or
geopolitically you will see them either
being uh there could be Downstream
effects or there could be effects of
that before before it actually happens
for example in 1989 when the uh Berlin
Wall fell in the USSR eventually
crumbled a tremendous amount of
geopolitical changes happened in those
years in the early '90s late 80s Etc new
nations were formed and much a lot of
stuff happened the uh Central Asian
republics became independent uh
Yugoslavia was broken up and and lots of
things happened there were Downstream
effects in Africa as well
so with the Advent of Technology like
Technologies like blockchain with the us
becoming the AI
superpower I believe that the US may be
on the verge of soon possibly rolling
out a digital dollar digital
currency and maybe the EU and all
Western nations may participate in that
and with and that would obviously
naturally be controlled from the US so
the US essentially will own and control
this currency that's what I think and
when this currency is rolled out a
digital currency then you don't really
need the US dollar I mean you can phase
it out slowly so I don't think the US
will allow its Supremacy its Primacy
Global Primacy and superpower status and
it's its currency status is the world's
reson Cur to just slip away like that
especially at the hands of Saudi Arabia
which you could say is whether you like
it or not it's a us wasal it's been one
since well the 20th century the middle
of the 20th century so the Saudis as I'm
I'm sure you will understand will do
nothing that will displease the US
significantly you may remember that when
the Jamal kogi incident
happened uh the Americans in the West
hounded and and uh
humiliated the Crown Prince Muhammad bin
Salman he was treated very very poorly
whenever he went to some G20 or whatever
he went he was marginalized he was
sideline nobody would speak to him only
Mr Putin and Mr Modi would speak to him
and so on so the Saudis know full well
what can happen what will happen if they
uh challenge the US in any way
whatsoever Every Nation knows that no
Nation can stand up to the US today the
US can destroy entire nation
like that so I think this is part of a
script I think we're going to see a move
to digital currencies and those digital
currencies whether it's a basket of
currencies or single currency will be
controlled by the US owned by the
US and maybe this is the beginning of
that phase so I don't think it it poses
a significant challenge to us uh to the
US superpower status to the US Supremacy
Etc I think it's part of a script that's
being played out right now okay next
question
Anand theal says namaskar what's your
take on the Indian army getting nagast
nag asra one the indigenously made Kami
Kaz drone some Reports say that the Army
is planning to get 5,000 of these drones
in the next three years I think it's a
it's a it's a good step I'm glad to see
this uh progress happening uh the 21st
century Warfare is different compared to
the 19th century Warfare we' have seen
uh how things are being are happening
differently in the Armenia aeran
conflict and also the Ukraine war
obviously the lessons of the Ukraine war
have to be heeded the battlefield
environment the battle space environment
is very different today in the 21st
century all these new technologies
coming in and loitering Munitions
suicide drones cic drones whatever you
want to call them are a very important
part of the new Battlefield environment
so these drones are typically 10 12 15
kilograms in weight lightweight things
you can lift them with one one hand okay
10 12 kilos I think the nag asra one is
about 12 kilos in weight and the Warhead
it carries or the what the the
ammunition it carries would be about
three to four kilos maybe three kilos so
the explosive charge is basically just
two or three kilos three kilos maybe so
that what does it do it it takes out
individuals it's an anti-personnel uh
weapon or maybe it can take out small
Vehicles as well so I've not seen the
details I'm sure a 3 kogam explosive
charge can take out a small to medium
vehicle or at least or disable
it for example a a personal carrier a
Jeep maybe even a tank if you hit it in
the right spot maybe at the top from the
turret or whatever so I'm glad this is
happening I believe this uh this drone
this lering drone has uh an endurance of
about 30 minutes so 30 minutes it can
fly which is a along the same lines as
the various drones that are being used
in the Ukraine conflict so it's it's the
same class of drone and I'm sure it's
been tested and now it's being inducted
I'm glad to see that uh 5,000 in the
next three years well I think you should
ramp up the numbers a bit or maybe we
should maybe it's just the first
iteration of a loitering drone U and I
think it's being manufactured by a
private company so I hope many more such
we systems are developed in India and
what what I I hope our planners and
strategists understand is that we need
large quantities of these things so I
can understand if the first iteration of
this weapon you only acquire 5,000 of
these over the next three years but once
you have a fully uh robust and you can
say final system that is the right thing
you can take in in a battlefield then
you need large quantities of that
because if you have a war let's say with
whoever let's say you have a two front
war on the one hand you have Pakistan on
the other hand you have China and
Chinese occupied Tibet then to fight
these two Nations you're going to need
lots and lots of these assets so overall
I would say great progress I'm glad to
see that India is not being left behind
we have tremendous engineers in India we
have lots of private companies that can
do wonderful work we should become a
technological superpower forget about
being a geopolitical superpower right
now let's become a Technologic iCal
superp power major power drun
manufacturing and other stuff and I
think we are seeing steps being taken in
the direction so overall great job and
let's
continue mcloven says do you think the
whole Manipur war is funded to cut the
eastern part from India maybe it was
planned all the way back in 47
look let's understand what's happening
uh forget about the 1947 angle the whole
process began in the 19th century in the
early 19th century I've spoken about
this multiple times I will not repeat
myself now what's happened look I've
been seeing this for the past one year
okay since May last year that this is a
geopolitical issue it's not a Law and
Order problem it's not some kind of um
you know some tribal group demanding
Justice or whatever it's not a local Law
and Order problem this is a geopolitical
issue that India is facing I've been
saying this for the past one year and
now there is corroboration of that and
my entire premise is that this is this
conflict is being funded by the same
forces that created the conflict the
problem by settling foreigners in India
beginning in the 19th century the
British started this Pro this process of
settling foreigners cookies inside India
by force okay forcibly it was not done
with the will and the consent of the
Manipur of the people of Manipur the
indigenous people of Manipur so these
cookies were settled over time and after
1947 after 1949 the Indian government
also continued the same stupid practice
because the Indian government has to
blindly ape the West right if the
British had some policies there must
have been good policies so the Indian
government continued the same stupid
policies the Indian government actually
went ahead and christianized the whole
significant portion of the northeast of
the Far East of India entire States
entire regions have been totally
christianized and so on so you know what
happens when when a region gets
christianized the Chinese understand
this very well the the Japanese
understood this in the 19th 17th century
Chinese also and so that brings in
external geopolitical influence in the
region now what's happening now you may
have heard about what shik Hina said
recently so let's put that on the screen
shik Hina what she said she said she
without naming the foreign Nations she
said that a foreign Nation wants an air
base in Bangladesh to carve out a
Christian state so these are two
separate things they want one an airbase
and two they want to carve out a
Christian state from you know not just
Bangladesh but so Myanmar and she did
not refer to India but I assure you it
it means India also and when we talk
about India it means Manipur and also
mizoram by the way also mizoram do not
forget mizoram
so so that's what she has said and she
said that she was offered a smooth
re-election campaign by a wh- skinned
man if she allowed the country to build
an air base in Bangladesh so which
tribal group wants to create a Christian
Nation in in out of Bangladesh out of
Burma out of India it is the cookies the
cookies are tribal group that that is
not even Burmese they do not speak the
Burmese language they don't practice
burmes Customs or culture and they owe
no no allegiance to Burma they came from
further east maybe the yunan region
which is currently part of China or some
other part of of the world and they are
fighting three nations Burma Bangladesh
and India and in India it's mainly the
people of Manipur are the victims they
are under H and more than half of
Manipur has been taken over by cookies
because the entire state is there's an
undemarcated no the border is demarcated
but it's an unfenced border it's an open
border with a free passage regime and
that problem was not create has been
around for decades so the current
government listen for whatever its fault
the current government has not created
the solution Mr modi's government has
not created this this situation they
have inherited this
problem Maybe could have been more alert
maybe maybe they should have known what
could be coming but well so there you
have it now so the Americans want let's
let's just name them the Americans want
to carve out a Christian Nation out of
Bangladesh Myanmar and parts of India a
Christian Nation so let us go to the map
my dear friends and let me explain what
the situation is H let's just speak
openly today
see India is becoming too large for its
boots India is progressing too fast so
the British created an artificial
Islamic Nation out of the western
regions of India Pakistan the world's
number one exporter of terrorism which
still stands today for now and now the
Americans who have inherited power from
the British Empire who are the
continuation of the British Empire want
to carve out a Christian Nation to the
east of India out of Burma out of parts
of Bangladesh and out of some Indian
States
so technically the this chis the parts
of the Indian States far east states
that will be part of this nation kiland
zenam whatever you want to call it they
will technically be part of India but
they'll be administered separately it's
already the situation is already there
today large parts of Manipur are Lawless
they are being administered by the
ragtag tribals and the Indian government
does not have much say there so the
Americans want to carve out a Christian
Pakistan the Christian Pakistan from
Burma banglades
and parts of the Far East of India
mainly Manipur but other states will
also be kind of touched by that and some
other States Territory will also be part
of that you could say perhaps mizoram
could be involved in that all right and
let's not even talk about mizoram right
now because it's a
whole Pandora's
box and the Americans also want an
island from the Bangladeshi so I have
spoken at length about uh the the
British Indian Ocean territory which is
actually controlled and and operated by
the Americans the Diego Garcia uh a
military base the Americans have a large
Air Force Station over here and they
also have a MAG a massive Naval Base
here which can uh accommodate entire
aircraft carriers so that allows the
Americans to project power in the Indian
Ocean region and you know uh apply
pressure in this region whenever they
need now they want another such station
in the Bay of Bengal so which island do
they want they want this Bangladeshi
Island over here I believe it's called
sa something St Martin's island or
something like that yeah St Martins
Island so it is a Bangladeshi Island but
it's off the coast of
Burma and it's a
reasonably uh well-sized Island they
could the Americans could build an Air
Force Base over here as well as a naval
base here and that will allow them to
pressurize every nation in this region
especially the nation that they that is
the focus Center of focus which is
India so now you may ask me why isn't
the Indian government doing anything
about this why isn't the Indian
government pushing back against the
cookies and the foreign involvement in
Manipur here's what will happen my dear
friends the moment the Indian government
takes any real action against the the
cookies who are terrorizing the natives
of of of Manipur here's what will happen
the moment the Indian government dares
to take any action the Americans will
accuse India of wides scale large scale
wide ranging human rights abuses and
they will impose the same same kind of
sanctions on India the kind of sanction
they have imposed on Burma as well as
Cuba and they will destroy the Indian
economy and bring India down to the
level of Cuba
okay so Mr Modi has a choice what do we
do what do you do the Americans are too
powerful there's nothing India can do if
they want to break India into pieces
absolutely nothing nothing so the best
solution is to have as little damage as
possible okay that is the situation we
are standing at today so it is entirely
possible that in the next by the end of
this decade there could be a Christian
Nation a Christian Pakistan in the Far
East of
India and some parts of that Nation will
be taken from Manipur and even even
mizoram could be part of that because
they are essentially the same people
misos zies same
thing so this is the game shik hassina
has has spoken about this she has not
spoken about Manipur she has not spoken
about India but learn to read between
the lines don't be like the the level of
seventh standard learn to read between
the lines
that is the deal the Americans want to
uh so that they can Pakistan is not
enough now for India we need two such
Terror Nations to keep India completely
hemmed in look look at this look at the
map so you will have Pakistan on the
west and this cookie Nation on the on
the East Burma will be disintegrated
into pieces okay Burma is is almost
doomed
now and you will have two Nations on
India's one on India Eastern side one on
India's western side and India will be
completely cut off from Southeast Asia
the we have plans to build roads and
Railways all that will be over we
already cut off from Central Asia and
Europe in Eurasia by Pakistan and and
Chinese occupied Tibet so the only
recourse India will have is to go by sea
or go by Air India is essentially a
landlocked Nation almost because of
these things and the Americans are now
actively creating an artificial nation
in the eastern part of India and they
wanted shik Hena to be to be part of
that obviously she did not agree and she
has actually been very courageous when
she's spoken about this and maybe she
will pay pay some price for that the
Americans don't don't forgive uh anyone
who does that but yeah so the reason she
has been able to stay in power is
because of Indian support in
Bangladesh
so the punishment for that is that
Bangladesh itself will be broken
now that's where we are we'll keep we'll
keep tracking this all
right okay Malik s says in the future if
a war happens between India and China
then is it possible that rather than
helping India the Americans will try to
engineer the breakup of India so that
they should eliminate a big upcoming
threat also is it the best scenario in
the American interest in which China and
India go to war resulting in a unipolar
world or will and will China and India
show majority in this case against the
West uh ask a very good question my
friend uh if there's a war between India
and China it will be a win-win situation
for the Americans because both are
nuclear powered nuclear armed States uh
both will possibly incur significant
damage if the war goes on Beyond a
certain amount of time if there's no
quick seiz
fire and that could help the Americans
immensely because China is the currently
the biggest threat from the economic
perspective the manufacturing so on so
for perspective for the US uh the
Russians are the biggest military threat
for the US and India is the one
long-term emerging threat for the US
from their perspective we don't threaten
anybody but they see anybody who's
emerging as a threat to them because
they don't want any emerging power in
the world the Americans so if India and
China go to war they will well they will
try and impose conditions on India okay
we we're willing to help you but you
know here are the
conditions and and I have made an entire
video about that so do I have it
somewhere open uh you can you can check
it out you can check it out I have a
video on this channel about what demands
the Americans will make in exchange for
help against China and even if they
eventually do help India it will be
minimal help which will essentially
ensure that
India emerges from this war situation
significantly diminished so they are not
anyone's friends they are nobody's
friends they're not even Australia or
the UK's friends they're no one's
friends they are the sole superpower and
they want to maintain that status when
you are the so superpower you are
jealous you you're jealous of anyone
who's who is potentially going to
emerge so
yeah so if if if the war happens it will
be great for them the ideal situation
for the US is that India and China blow
each other's brains out and totally
destroy each other and then they can
peacefully deal with Russia in their own
sweet time that's the ideal situation
for them so what should India and China
do I mean China needs to behave a little
bit we don't threaten
China they have been antagonizing India
they have been trying to bite around at
India's territory and now that India is
been ramping up infrastructure
development in the in the Northern parts
in the Tibet bordering regions they they
go ahead with this galwan clash and
whatnot it is entirely their fault that
the situation is bad the relations
between the two nations are bad it's
China's fault they're also pressuring
other nations they're trying to
interfere in Nepal they're trying to
bully
Bhutan the Chinese have themselves to
blame for their their bad relationship
with
India they have steadfastly refused to
demarcate the India Tibet border for
decades we didn't it's not our fault
it's their fault so uh I think it is the
Chinese who need to show some amount of
maturity and eventually you keep on
doing that going to see consequences so
they have been renaming parts of India
to Chinese names now India has gone
ahead and renamed parts of Tibet to
Indian names or or Indian uh that two
names that we have decided so you know
what that means when the Indian
government officially goes ahead and
renames 30 places in Tibet what does it
mean it means that India has reopened
the Tibet
issue understand that who is to blame
for this are we to blame for that no the
Indian government has done the right
thing so I think the Chinese need to
demonstrate some more some amount of
maturity they have been uh behaving in a
very childish manner a very you know
immature manner they they should
understand that India is not a threat to
them India doesn't threaten China India
doesn't claim Chinese territory India
has never started a war with China India
the past 2,000 years has given so much
to China without asking anything return
and I think that that is something that
that you know Works them actually with
Chinese Communist Party um I hope that
India and China don't go to war I hope
the Chinese don't start a war if a war
happens between India and China it will
be started by the Chinese not by
India it it is in the in both Nations
interests not to good good war and I
hope that China will show
maturity in this matter but the Chinese
seem to see the world from a zero sum
perspective that for them to win
everybody else has to lose
um they don't want to coexist peacefully
with anybody they've been pressurizing
Russia also they have renamed some parts
of Russia as well yeah so the problem is
the Chinese Communist
party so you know so if the two Nations
go to war it's going to only end up
benefiting the West it's going to end up
benefiting the us so I hope that mature
Minds will pre Prevail in China India
has behaved maturely India has shown the
utmost restraint thus
far so I hope China will show some
maturity I will appeal to the Chinese
government today please show some
maturity India is not your
enemy India is your elder brother
civilization all right and we need to
get along because the in the long run we
have to coexist India is not going
anywhere India is not going anywhere no
matter what you how much you desire that
so shows some maturity and let's let's
get
along okay next question is by shran
earlier there were plans for a north
south trade corridor from which India
could get access to Europe for trade but
then the US and Iran sanctions slowed it
and now even America even Armenia is not
stable then last year the US came up
with the India middle east Europe
corridor and soon after that a conflict
started with hisbah and and Hamas and
Israel so do you think that all the
major Powers don't want India to get a
trade route with
Europe you see India is a growing
economy and if India keeps on growing at
6 7 8% whatever percentage per year for
the next 20
years in first of all in the next three
to four five years maximum India is
going to be the third largest economy in
the world it's going to be the US China
India and if India keeps growing the way
it is growing then India could
eventually by 2050 perhaps even surpass
China that is a big problem for the West
this n this civilization that they had
almost destroyed Stamped Out sucked
everything out of it is still alive and
now now it's again emerging out of the
debris out of the destruction caused by
the
British and there is this Resurgence of
of some kind of national pride in India
most Indians are still deeply deeply de
mentally colonized and deracinated but
there is some pride that's reemerging in
India and that is that sets off alarm
bells in the west so yes it is not in
their interest if India does well they
want to utilize India in certain ways
India has limited utility like like I've
said for the West they would like India
to be an exporter of services not Goods
or if if India exports Goods then it
should be only the goods that they they
desire they don't want India to become a
major manufacturing power they would
like to Outsource the manufacturing now
not not in any more to China they want
to seek other options but maybe Vietnam
and other countries but hopefully not
India they don't want to turn India into
the next
China and uh and obviously they would
like to use India as a counterbalance to
China but they would like to
counterbalance India also with Pakistan
and in a new nation called cooki
land so uh they are not India's friends
they don't want to see India develop
infrastructure uh you know trade routes
supply chain Etc with Europe India has
been very nicely isolated the past 70 80
years I mean look at the map why was
Pakistan created to cut India off from
Eurasia India historically has had
thousands of years of connections with
Central Asia and Europe and Eurasia that
has been entirely cut off thanks to the
great wonderful founding fathers of
India who accepted this in
1947 so India is completely cut off from
from
Eurasia so what India can do is we can
uh you know take the help of Nations
friendly Nations like Iran and go
through ports like chabahar there is a p
chabahar here and we can access
Afghanistan bypassing Pakistan and even
access access Central Asia and Europe
and Iran was to be one of the uh staging
points for the like you say the north
south International north south
transport and trade Corridor but that's
uh the Americans want would not like
that to go ahead the other one the the
middle India Middle East imch India
middle east Europe trade Corridor it's
not happening right now because of the
uh Hamas Israel war in India recently
acquired the chabahar port on a lease of
10 years at least one terminal and the
Americans threatened sanctions against
India once this happened so it's very
clear that the US forget about the major
Powers there are no major powers in the
west there's only one major power in the
west which is the US and all other
Western powers are wasal of the US the
puppets so the Americans do not want to
see India grow they do not want to see
forget about Rising they don't want
India to grow at all India should be cut
down to size and this kooky land thing
this new nation thing is all a means of
doing
that so yes you are right the only thing
I will I would like to amend is that
there are no Western major Powers
there's only one major power in the west
it's the US and they do not want to see
India grow they don't want to see India
rise they want to cut India down to size
and use India for specific purposes for
The Limited utility they have for India
and that's it so it's going to be
challenging for India how does
India deal with
this so you either just give to the west
and just allow them to use you in
whatever way you want which means that
you will eventually become the next
Japan you
destroyed or you resist but then you pay
some price for that so these are the big
dilemas that Mr Modi has to Grapple with
so yes they invite Mr Modi to the G7
Summit they give him a center position
and all that uh but there's a prise they
surprise and so they on the one hand
they're they're shaking hands with you
on the other hand they're twisting a
knife in your back at the same time
that's what's happening and you got to
smile and Shake Hands while knife is
being Twisted in your back that is
international Rel that is geopolitics
that is diplomacy geopolitics is the
rule of the
Jungle okay Priyanka Tanja says could
you talk about how does a powerful
leader like Wladimir Putin operate
considering the constant threat of
assassination at any given point in time
surely he would have lots of internal
enemies apart from the usual external
ones so Cons considering the constant
threat of assassination how does he
manage to remain safe keep all his State
secrets intact and continue leading his
Nation okay so this applies to not just
Vladimir Putin it applies to Shi Jinping
it applies to Narendra Modi it applies
to whoever is the the president of the
US and it applies to all major world
leaders the ones that really matter in
the case of the US the president well in
63 a president was assassinated nothing
much changed but when it comes to real
world leaders so in the US what I mean
is that the president isn't really the
person who holds real power the
president like Douglas Adams said his
job is to
distract people the public from where
the real power
lies so the US president is essentially
Zaford bble bble Brocks in case you know
what I mean anyway when it comes to real
world leaders like uh Mr Putin like Mr
Shi Jinping like Mr Modi even m m a TR
they always face the possibility
that somebody would want to assassinate
them that threat has to be considered as
a 24 Seven threat as as as as long as at
least if you are the security people of
the of the leader Mr Putin Mr Modi Mr
she whoever it is you have to consider
that the the leader is under constant
24x7 threat of assassination so there
are measures that are
taken to ensure that such a thing
doesn't happen
and uh so when it comes to the security
and all that all that stuff I would
suggest that you read the Earth shastra
where is it somewhere here behind me
okay so in the
arastra vishnugupta chanakya writes
about this that what are the threats
that uh the the emperor usually has to
live under and what are the counter
measures what are the mitigating uh
actions and and processes that you need
to have to ensure the the security
of the emperor what are what are the
cordance of security he needs to have
and so on he was referring to Vish he
was referring to Chandra gup Moria
obviously but later Emperors like Ashok
Etc would also have even more enhanced
security so you need to have spies you
need to have intelligence you need to
have multiple cordance of security
everybody needs to be under surveillance
even your own people need to be under
surveillance one spies on this guy the
other guy spies on that guy that sort of
thing this actually happens in the world
okay we may not see it we may be
completely oblivious to it but in the
real world when it comes to that level
of leadership it is all there okay so
Vladimir Putin obviously um like what
chanaka writes even the food has to be
tested every single meal has to be
tasted by somebody else and you wait for
half an hour and that somebody else is
fine then you go ahead and and and give
it to the leader and so on and today you
have slow acting poison so that you have
to be even more careful poison Maybe
become may may act after what 72 hours
after a week who knows slow acting
longlasting
poisons U and so on so there's a lot
that goes into the security of a leader
so that ensures that the leader is safe
and there are obviously there is State
secrecy how to keep things classified
how to keep multiple levels of
classification secret above secret top
secret above top top secret and so on
and what are the measures for what are
the protocols for each layer of secrecy
and so on you only give out information
on a need to know basis I think even
normal people need to understand this
but normal people won't understand that
even those who are not leaders even
those who are not in government need
need to understand that you give
information on only on a need to know
basis you don't give information for
free to everybody I'm talking about
personal
information okay that's what I mean so
uh all that is there are protocols there
are there are processes for all these
things so that's how it's done it's it's
very complicated it is very high stakes
but yes every nation has its own
protocols its own processes its own
procedures its own sets of personnel
that handle all these things and that's
how a leader is kept safe and
functioning at the highest level and all
the state Secrets remain secrets and so
on and then when when a leader travels
there's a whole Entourage that travels
with the leader not just the political
Entourage and the communications people
and all that but also security Personnel
at various levels you go into a foreign
country and you uh check into a hotel
obviously you check into a hotel
somewhere then you know the entire Hotel
can be commanded by the by the people of
the of the nation by the security
Personnel or at least a couple of floors
above and below the floor on which the
leader is staying the entire place is is
swept down for SEC with for security
measures you know uh bugs you test for
bugs and you test for what not um and so
on so it's it's very it's very detailed
it's very intricate it's very laborious
but that's what needs to be done
especially when it comes to the security
of a leader that genuinely matters not
fake leaders who are replaceable
disposable fungible but real
leaders okay
coner conquer conqueror YT whatever okay
asks what's the primary force which
drives history is it geography is it
economics is it Warfare is it culture is
it willpower is it emotions is it great
is it great men and so on so um what is
the primary force that drives history
well there are numerous forces that
drive history one of the things that is
should be obvious I mean it's I'm sure
nothing is obvious but one of the main
drivers of history is human nature you
will see that uh history repeats itself
it's cyclical it happens in Cycles in
China they call that the dynastic Cycles
a dynasty emerges and becomes powerful
and rules for a long period of time and
then eventually it it loses the Mandate
of Heaven which means it loses control
of the nation and then it falls and then
there's a extended period of chaos maybe
a few decades maybe a century or so then
a new Dynasty emerges and the same thing
happens over and over and over again
similarly you see the rise and fall of
Kingdoms the rise and fall of Empires
even the rise and fall of
civilizations and so on so why do we see
these things happen in Cycles it's
because human nature is non-changing it
is Everlasting the same needs desires
wants aspirations Ambitions that we have
today the same were in play 5,000 years
ago and the same cycles of history were
occurring even then but we had different
technology so it happened at a different
different pace and at a different scale
today it can happen on a global scale
the same things so one of the forces
that drives history is human nature
human
psychology the other force that drives
history is Conquest
Conquest okay civilization doesn't
matter civilization can fall you may be
the most sophisticated civilization but
a rag dag bunch of tribals can come and
destroy you if they have better better
tactics and they're focused only on one
objective which is Warfare so I think
it's human nature and it is Conquest
obviously G geography plays a factor in
all these things economics plays a
factor uh culture culture yeah okay some
people are more warlike because they
have more primitive cultures or more
warlike cultures people who who you
know uh peoples who emerge from uh
regions that uh have scarcity typically
are hardier and they are more focused on
warfare because they have to scr around
for a living and and there's very so
much so so little uh resources that you
to fight each other constantly for
whatever res little resources exist so
if a leader can you know bring everybody
together then they can go with that same
uh lifestyle they can conquer other
nations much easier even though those
nations may be culturally civilization
way Superior to this rag taged bunch of
tribals and so on so and obviously there
is the Great Men Theory which means that
all historical changes geopolitical
changes are driven by the actions of
Great Men which could have more than a
small grain of Truth in them so it is
Conquest it is human
nature and maybe it is the actions of a
few Great Men in history some can I
think of any great women who have
changed the course of history in the in
a certain region maybe in some cases
there may
be um okay but yeah we call it the great
man Theory and there's also the violent
ape Theory which means that we at the
core are just violent apes look at our
closest Cousins the
chimpanzees they behave just like us
they have gang Warfare they have
Warlords they have territorial disputes
they have senseless violence brutality
they are very much like us the
chimpanzees we have certain certain more
levels of sophistication some of some of
us belong to cultures that are rather
civilized India bhat wassh has been a
great civilization for the past 10,000
years but at the end of the day it's
Conquest it's
violence and uh human nature that is the
driver driving force of history and
Conquest has
well why why do we conquer well if you
ask some people why do you conquer
they'll say I conquer because I can but
it's about ambition it's about greed
it's about want to control more you want
more resources and so on so forth Etc
you
know okay Imran Imran naimi says why are
the names of the languages different in
Turkey speaking countries but they all
use almost the same grammar in words
they can all communicate with each other
such as turkey aeran istan turkistan
kirgistan K kazakistan Taran Etc why are
the names of the languages in these
countries not called turkey or Turkish
why do they have different names for
example in England the US Australia they
call their language English otherwise
they are geographically very far apart
and they have they have their own
accents and unique words as well also uh
Persian speaking countries such as Iran
Afghanistan Tajikistan have different
language names too what's the reason
okay
so good good question interesting
question so there are nations that are
Persian speaking Nations Persia
obviously Iran uh Tajikistan they speak
Persian there parts of Afghanistan they
speak Persian there um most Afghans
speak PTO the actual native language of
Afghanistan but Dari Dari is also an
official language State language in
Afghanistan and that is the Afghan
version of Persian which is Persian
itself Tajikistan also they speak their
own variant of Persian persan
and in Iran they speak
persan but so why is persan called Dari
in Afghanistan and why why why that and
when it comes to the turkey nations in
Turkey in Turkey they speak the Turkish
language in aeran they speak azeri in
usbekistan they speak usbek in turkistan
they speak turkman in kyrgistan they
speak the kirgis language in Kazakhstan
they speak the kazak language tatarstan
which is part of China right now they
speak the Tatar language but these
languages are mutually more or less
intelligible so you can communicate with
each other despite speaking apparently
different languages why is that because
all these turkic languages are part of
the turkic language
family in
India especially in in northern and
western India it doesn't matter whether
your mother tongue is this or that or
that you can kind of understand each
other if you are a Bengali speaking
person and uh you communicate to a Hindi
speaking person in in Bengali and that
person answers back in Hindi you can
more or less understand each other if
you are a marati speaking person and you
speak to somebody who is a native whose
native language is Gujarati you can
speak to each other in your own language
and you can kind of understand each
other that's the kind of thing it is the
language is are very closely connected
and related the turkic languages there
have been other languages turkic
languages like chagatai Etc that no
longer
exist and so the languages have evolved
over time the Turks the turkic peoples
they spread all across Central Asia in
very very distant disparate parts of
Central Asia geographically
significantly
distant separated from each other and
that's why there was less communication
for centuries and that's how languages
evolved and diverged to certain degrees
from each other and acquire different
names but they are all turkic languages
which is why they are mutually
intelligible similarly persan well
because of
History um see person the personal
language has evolved over time about
3,000 years ago it was very much similar
to Sanskrit it was a daughter language
of
Sanskrit um and there is ample evidence
of that read the beist bhagana
inscription and so on and then the
language evolved over time portion and U
it has been more or less standardized
the persan language in the past roughly
1,000 years because of the incredible
influence of the shame of fosi
and fi well let's let's not talk about
fi and his opinions about various
matters but yeah so fi the Shah fi has
been an extremely influential text in
standardizing the personal language
which is why the personal language
hasn't changed much in the past Thousand
Years th roughly Thousand Years roughly
roughly and it's it's spoken in
Tajikistan and Afghanistan and because
it's been such a long time the languages
have slightly slightly been altered and
they have taken different names so in
Afghanistan they call it Dari which is
nothing but Persian when it comes to
English well the English phenomenon is
very recent the English conquered the
much of the world in the past like 300
or so years so it's a very new
phenomenon it's not a very ancient
language uh what's the origin of the
English Modern English language it's
it's a Germanic language okay it's not a
brittonic language the brittonic peoples
were Celtic peoples the
English were Germanic the Angles and the
Saxons were they came from Germany they
were they were a Germanic people they
conquered the British Isles and they
smashed everything in existence and
enslaved and destroyed the
Kelts and then the Saxons the angal and
Saxons became the Saxons they had their
little kingdoms on the British Islands
you know primitive little kingdoms like
North Umbria and meria and
East Anglia and whatever then there was
a viking age from about 880 to about
1050 ad roughly 250 years when great
Vikings came and had their fun in in
England and then you had
a a descendant of one of these Vikings
his name was William Gom luat he was a
Norman so he was called William the
bastard but he conquered England at the
age of something and then he was called
William the
Conqueror and then
England fell out of the so then the the
Normans who were descendants of Vikings
intermingled with the French they took
over England and the Saxons lost all
sovereignty of England so for a time you
had the Saxon language that was
prevalent so initially it was a it was
the the pictish and various Celtic
languages GIC Etc Irish old Irish Etc
that were the major languages in England
in the British Isles then you had Saxon
the Saxon language for a few centuries
the Angles and Saxons conquered British
islands in the four about fourth fifth
centuries ad roughly okay you can maybe
off by a century or so but you can look
it
up then in the year 1066 the Normans
take over so the sax Saxon language
becomes marginalized and the Norman
language becomes the lingua of kanka in
England and the normal language you
could say it was French okay it was more
or less French so for a few centuries
the nobility the aristocracy of England
the Nobles they speak French and The
Peasants The Peasants they speak Saxon
and then eventually these languages
combined and the Modern English language
eventually emerges out of all this so
English Today is a Germanic language
it's a reasonably recent language and
these nations the England the US
Australia New Zealand Canada well they
all speak this very recent language so
it's these are these are cultures with
with very little
time that they have existed and that's
why it is like that when it comes to the
turkic languages the the various Nations
that speak persan and the various Indo
Arian languages these are extremely
ancient the turkic languages would have
been around for about 2,000 plus years
the origin The Originators the the the
progenitors of the Turks are the ient XU
who emerged from the region of Mongolia
today and they were the Huns and they
were the you could say the parent ethnic
group of the Mongolians as well as the
Turks so the turkic languages you could
say are descendants of the old hunnik
language which existed about 2 and a
half thousand years ago so that's how
ancient the turkic language family is
roughly the Persian language family goes
back to at least 1, 1,500 BC which is 3
and a half thousand years before that
before which it was part of the Indian
language family and the Indian language
family goes
back let's say 10,000 years at least so
that's how you have all that
okay okay rudrajit sarar says Namibia
and South Africa once used to be a
single country then how did the country
break up what roles did the two
superpowers and their allies play in
this issue let's go to the map where is
the Namibia yes so we go to
Africa and you go to the southern part
of Africa and there you have South
Africa Leo masu and you have
Namibia so what is the deal about
Namibia so the origin what's the origin
of this nation called Namibia so it
originates in the 1870s or 1880s when
the Germans the
Germans took control of this part of
Africa which is roughly today is
Namibia maybe some parts of Botswana may
also be have been part of that so the
Germans colonized this region and it is
rich in certain kinds of resources okay
homework look it up what resources are
prevalent are abundant in Namibia very
interesting resources okay by the way
Namibia very interesting very lucrative
so the Germans were in control of this
territory from the roughly roughly 1880s
until let's say 1918 1919 end of the
first World War which Germany lost so
Germany loses the first world war and
then this this this land this this let a
nation Namibia uh begins to be
administered from South Africa but it is
technically still a separate nation the
two nations were never a single country
they were technically always separate
countries now South Africa has an
interesting history itself obviously
originally African then um the Dutch
enter this region and they they the
Dutch had created two Nations in South
Africa or two territories in South
Africa one was orange free country or
transval and the other was what there
was another one which I can't remember
right now okay these were the africaner
people and eventually the British took
over this region and there were two BO
Wars one was in the 1880s if my memory
serves me right please look it up and
fact check me I may be off by a decade
or so roughly 80s the first bore War the
bores was where were Dutch origin
African people they fought the British
for their independence so the first B
war was in the 1880s the second bore war
was in the early 20th century 1902 or
something and Mr Gandhi Mr bandas Gandhi
wanted India to fight on behalf of the
British against the Dutch and the
British rejected his his his request
because the British were obviously uh
not willing to give weapons in the arms
of Indians because then well you know
there could it's could lead to other
problems uh so Mr Gandhi's request was
denied and he had to be content by with
driving ambulances and helping the
British serving the British in other
ways against the the boers when the
boers were defeated in the second B war
and they were maltreated horribly the
British created concentration camps for
the boers and they starved their
children to death in that wonderful
people the British and South Africa came
under British rule entirely
and Mr Gandhi he was he was dispatched
to India roughly 1915 or so by the
British to serve a different purpose
there anyway we're talking about Namibia
so after this end of the first world war
Namibia when Germany lost Namibia came
under the control of South Africa it was
administered by from South Africa and
obviously it was exploited the people
had no agency they had no Freedom there
was no democracy there were no human
rights it was the same system maybe even
harsher system than what you had in
South Africa in South Africa you had the
apar system we know that very well right
hopefully I hope I don't know what they
you you're taught in education in the
Indian education system but there was
the system of apoide in South Africa and
now the question so that is how it was
now the question is what was the role of
the two superpowers so the Soviets were
backing uh this nation north of Namibia
called Angola there was a long Civil War
there which was a proxy war the
Americans did not want Soviet influence
in this region so they they supported
various they armed various proxy groups
to fight the Soviets and the government
of Angola and then you had a long long
long Civil War in Angola the Soviets
supported freedom for Namibia Namibia
was under South African Administration
occupation whatever you want to call it
it was under a brutal apide regime and
they had a Freedom Movement called
Southwest
people's s w Southwest African people's
organization swapo and their leader in
the later part of the history was a guy
called Sam Noma who eventually became
the first president of Namibia so the
Soviets were in favor of the
independence of Namibia the Americans
supported South Africa's brutal apide
regime which was brutally crushing down
on crushing all all attempts to fight
for freedom in Namibia so the Americans
as they often are or they often were
were on the wrong side of History they
supported the brutal South African apide
regime then in 1989 the Berlin Wall
Falls and the USSR begins to
disintegrate and then there's no more
USSR influence in Africa and then the
Americans they change tactics and they
start the negotiations in South Africa
for the end of apide and they also
ensure that Namibia is given its
independence I think in 1990 or
something look it up look it up if
you're interested and Mr Sam Noma
becomes the first president or or leader
Prime Minister President whatever it was
of Namibia that is the deal so namia IIA
and South Africa were always two
separate countries technically even
though Namibia was ruled by South
Africa uh and it all ends in 1990 when
roughly 1990 plus or minus one or two
years look it up when Namibia is is
granted offered offered Independence on
South African terms and that is the deal
interesting history Namibia has very
interesting resources
okay asak Kip says what was Wich burning
how and when did it begin why is not is
it not spoken about
much well it there are certain interests
that would not like you to know about
this and you that would not like people
to speak about this certain interests
certain vested interests in the world
now ask yourself who rules the world
it's the Western Nations that rule the
world right it is the West that actually
rules the world the so-called
rules-based
Global Order who who who is the Super
cop that runs that it's the US the US is
an outroot of of the British it is a
continuation of of the British Empire
the British are Europeans Western
Europeans and we know the religious
angle in that Christianity so all of
that comes together to ensure that we
don't speak about Wich bur burning too
much because that makes Europeans and
Christians look bad nowadays they are
like Christianity needs to go and some
other religions need to be brought in
that's okay that's their their their
interests keep
changing but historically it's been like
so now the question is what is witch
burning what was witch
burning so we have to look back at the
proper context of History Europe used to
once it had a different culture once
Europe the whole of Europe the old
Indo-European culture which was an off
fruit of the old even more ancient Vic
culture same Gods same practices and so
on women had had a exalted status in
society in the old Indo European culture
it was a polytheistic
culture and no monotheism and so on so
that is how Europe used to
be in the last of the great European
polytheists where were you could see the
Vikings and the slaves in the Slavic
regions polytheism persisted until what
the 16th 17th even 18th century perhaps
even 19th century even now there are
there are Pagan movements in the Slavic
world even in the tonic world nowadays
assat and all that now going back going
back to the origin so Europe once had a
polytheistic culture just like India's
culture probably it was an offshoot of
the Indian culture old Indian culture
going back 10,000 years
now when at the end of the Viking age
around the year 1050 roughly in the 11th
century uh Christianity began began
became a major force in Europe so
Christianity had been officially had
been the official religion of the Roman
Empire centuries before that dating back
to the rule of Constantine who ruled
from byzantion which is Constantinople
currently part of turkey for now uh but
it Christianity had not spread across
Europe until the 11th or so Century
centuries it had spread to parts of
Europe but not all over Europe so then
there were you know you must have heard
about the Crusades Richard the liar
heart and his friends and his allies
European allies Western European allies
they go and invade
uh the region of
Israel that region Lebanon Israel Etc
and they want to liberate Jerusalem from
the so-called
sarasin and one of the great leaders of
the sarasin was Saladin
Salah and he dealt them significant blow
in the battle of the horns of hatin look
that interesting story there we'll not
go there right now uh but yes so you had
the Crusades you must have heard of the
Crusades but there were Northern
Crusades also in Which Europeans were
attacked and their Lifestyles
livelihoods destroyed and their
indigenous culture and religion smashed
out of existence brutally brutally
Through Blood through bloody
means and Northern Europe Etc became
christianized as a consequence of these
repeated so-called Northern
Crusades so Europeans attacking
Europeans Europeans destroying European
culture just to spread Christianity and
eventually the whole of Europe became
Christian but it is it is not easy to
Stamp Out traditional you know long
existing culture for example in India
the people of Goa where were forcibly
converted to Christianity but they were
practicing Hinduism in in secret and
then because of that the Portuguese
brought in the Inquisition that fellow
who what's his name I forget the name
his name starts with x f or X or
something I forget the guy's name that
that individual he brought in the
Inquisition in
Goa even though he may not have been
Portuguese but doesn't matter um that
fellow somehow the name slips out of my
mind so the Brit the the Europeans the
Christians did the same thing in Europe
they brought in the
Inquisition to stamp out any remnants of
pagan
culture and one of the things about the
old Indo-European culture was that you
had gender roles and and what they would
today call toxic masculinity so genders
had roles men did the hard work the
heavy lifting the the the field work the
the fighting if you were a soldier the
field work if you if you were a farmer
the hammering if you were a metal Smith
and so on and women took care of the
house and took care of of healthcare and
all that gender roles how horrible and
primitive the world used to be just
imagine that imagine that so women were
in charge of healing they had ancient
knowledge of herbs in India what do we
call that we call it
aured so the women the women folk of
Europe traditionally were in charge of
healing and they had that superpower
they had the knowledge ancient knowledge
that could that gave them the power of
life or death over people and obviously
it was used for good mostly hopefully I
guess to to heal people now that was a
major impediment in the path of the
church the church despised women I mean
look it's not a controversial thing I'm
saying over here look at the history of
the church the Vatican how many female
popes have you had how many female
cardinals have you had in the past 2,000
whatever
years okay so let's not even call that
statement controversial not even try so
the church despised women they saw them
they wanted women to have second class
status in society and historically women
were healers they were revered so the
church said any woman who has any such
knowledge is to be declared an agent of
Satan she consorts with the Devil with
Lucifer
himself and then this book became
popular the malus malarum the Hammer of
the witches which was a manual that that
taught you that gave you detailed
instructions in in as to in how to
identify how to identify witches and how
to punish them various forms of of of
uh joint manipulation and various uh
tactics and methods to to loosen
people's tongues essentially torture and
how to kill them through brutal ways and
how to identify the the signs and
symptoms of a person being a witch and
even were used to be accused of being
witches and this began the The Craze of
witch killing witch burning in Europe
and hundreds of thousands of women where
innocent women were burned
alive or drowned or
pressed if you don't know what pressing
is look it up so they were either burned
most most of them were burned some were
drowned and drowning was a
test and some were pressed Etc and this
was a reign of terror and for a couple
of centuries at least the second most
popular book in Europe was the malos
maleficarum it was written by a couple
of Christian
priests so that's what Witch buring is
was these days thankfully it's not there
that was the dark history of Europe and
it even made its rared its ugly head in
North America read about the Salem Witch
Trials okay and why is it not mentioned
much because it is an inconvenient fact
they would like to accuse us of being
primitive we were the ones who burned
our women folk alive Sati pra and lots
and lots and millions of of Indians
innocent Indians have been this has been
put into their heads that our ancestors
were were barbarians misogynic
barbarians and once a woman became a
video widow she would be burned alive
that's what lots of Indians think today
they've been taught this because your
education system is designed to make you
think make you believe these lies
so that's what witch burning was and
that's why they would not like to speak
about that they would like to rather
speak about fictitious artificially
created atrocity narratives like Sati
and whatnot in
India so
yeah rodit sarar again says was Hawaii
uninhabited before the European
colonization of the island if not then
did the native Hawaiian suffer the same
Fates as the Native Americans good
question let's first of all let's see
where Hawaii is so we go eastwards
eastwards into the Pacific Ocean and in
the middle of the Pacific North Pacific
we have these islands somewhere in
between uh Eastern Asia and the west
coast of the Americas and this these are
the Hawaiian Islands it's an archipelago
a cluster of islands okay uh so you have
the Hawaiian Islands
here and uh and these islands were not
uninhabited before the Europeans arrived
so some of you may be aware of Hawaii
it's a very famous very popular tourist
destination very nice climate and
surfing and beaches and and whatever
else and uh apparently exotic culture
and all that and it's it's the it's one
of the America it's one of the states of
the United States the US has 50 states
Hawaii is one of those so the Americans
annexed Hawaii sometime in the late 19th
century if I'm not mistaken okay you can
look up the exact date when it happened
but the Americans annexed Hawaii by
force forcible annexation so when Mr
Putin wants to take over parts of
Ukraine it's it's very naughty it's very
bad it's very evil it's very brutal it's
very dictatorial but when the US annexes
Hawaii by force it's perfectly
Democratic and natural when the US takes
over large chunks of Mexico by force
It's Perfectly Normal it's perfectly
nice because the US does it so it's fine
so the Hawaiians were a Polynesian
people and they have been present in
Hawaii for at least 1700 years maybe
2,000 years maybe
more and so like I said there are poian
people related to the various Pacific
island people in French Polynesia uh
Tonga the K Island Solomon Islands etc
etc etc the South Pacific Islands and so
on
hungara and Hawaii so they were they are
Polynesian people so what happened once
the Europeans started colonizing Hawaii
first of all most of the land of the
Hawaiian people was taken over by the
Europeans who established plantations
and whatnot over
there secondly
um more than 90% of the native
population died out was killed off or
died out you can see it whichever way
you like the nice way of of of looking
at it is that maybe the Europeans
brought in illnesses that these uh
Native people were had never been
exposed to and
so you know illnesses like influenza and
small poox Etc killed off lots of these
people whatever happened the fact is
that more than 90% of the natives were
they died out some of them were killed
off some of them died of illness
whatever more than 90% that is very much
the G word isn't it
genocide the similar thing happened in
North America in South America America
in North America the British and the
French killed off most of the natives
and completely marginalized the rest
today in if you go to Canada if you go
to the US these unfortunate natives of
the land are forced to live in
reservations which are like the worst
territory with no real
amenities and
uh well they they are called Indians and
they they are treated like second class
or third class citizens in Canada you
have Starlight tours I'm not sure if
this still happen but Google Starlight
tours horrific practices that the
Canadian po police
had and the other way of of
marginalizing the natives in North
America and South America is by
destroying their ethnic racial let's say
Purity how dare I speak of ethnic Purity
racial Purity huh so and and religion of
of course so today most natives in North
America would be
Christians I don't know if their native
culture religion even exists anymore and
most of them are no longer even pure
native they are all mixed with the
Invaders occupiers of the territory a
similar thing has happened in Hawaii
their language has been wiped out
everyone speaks English now the there
must be very few people in Hawaii who
actually speak the original native
language of Hawaii their indigenous
culture has been exoticized the hola
dance is is acceptable but no other form
of native culture is acceptable except
what is
allowed the native religion no longer
exists everybody has been converted to
Christianity and lots of the people have
been inter have intermixed with the
Invaders and occupiers settlers settler
settler colonialists of the land so it
has been a demic and cultural
genocide so yes you are right the native
Hawaiians have essentially suffered the
same fate is the Native Americans in
Northern in North and South America but
but the West is still the Arbiter of
Human Rights and democracy they they
still are the supreme authority on human
rights and democracy doesn't matter what
they've done and are still doing that's
okay if they do
it NAIA says why is it so that our
education system has never bothered to
teach us about the Mongol history of the
Chinese history it is one thing to not
teach Indian history but why is it so
that why is it that they were complet
these other histories of the world were
completely s sideline not mentioned was
there any agenda behind this to again
make us unaware of what happened in the
world and in our own country you know
when I was a kid when I was a
kid India was a very different
country the closest country that exists
today I would say is North
Korea in the 1980s in the 1990s India
was so so different it was an insular
country an inward looking country you
had one television channel across the
country and you would have news every
day and 80% of the news would be so and
so Minister said so and so thing in so
and so speech so and so Minister said
something else in some some other speech
the Prime Minister opened inaugurated so
and so project he went and cut the
ribbon here and so and so Minister did
this and so on what ministers have said
today that was news and you would get
next to no information about what was
happening outside of
India nothing so Indians in the 1980s
and 1990s up till that time did not
until the
1980s beginning of the 1990s India
started opening up so until the 1980s
Indians had no idea of what was outside
India they had never seen a foreign
person India was completely insular just
like North Korea the people were not
allowed to know what was happening
outside the
country that's what India was like so
are you surprised the education system
has is also like that why are you
surprised they wanted the the rulers of
India the the post 1947 rulers of India
wanted Indians to be completely cut off
from the rest of the world they did not
want to see India prosper and grow it
was a captive population like a
population of sheep a shepher will take
care of his population but they will
keep it in ated isolated from the rest
of the world and the Sheep are
eventually for Slaughter
right so the there was no economic
growth nothing it was all rent seeking
much of that still exists in some forms
there is obviously progress now so
that's how India was and the most
dangerous thing in a cap captive
population is that you understand how
the world works that that is dangerous
if you really understand how the world
works so you should not understand how
the world works and how are you how how
are you to be made to not understand how
the world works by giving you no
information about the
world and telling you lies about the
world so when it comes to your own
history my friends they have been lying
to you for decades everything most of
what you are being taught today is is
sprinkled with lies and distortions 80%
truth 20% lies lots of omissions lots of
censorships lots of distortion that's
about your own
history second they will not teach you
your culture at all this is the only
nation only civilization in the world
where kids are not taught their own
culture so generation upon generation we
becoming more and more deracinated the
15 year olds of today what connection do
they have to their ancestral culture
nothing nothing whatsoever so in a few
decades India is going to
be will will maybe not even be a Hindu
country of course we are officially a
secular country right so it's a project
to destroy India's culture and when it
comes to world history you should not be
taught world history
because then you will understand more
how the world really works so all they
will teach you is British history in the
wonderful things the great
uh um favors the British did to
India that's all they will teach you
they won't teach you Chinese history
Mongol history you know Central Asian
history European history they'll teach
you none of that especially the history
of the I mean if you understand history
if you taught history properly you will
start to understand cause and effect
that is what they don't want you to
understand they don't want you to
understand
causality because then you can see
through their
actions because the same forces the same
agendas that have shaped world history
in the past are today shaping
geopolitics and internal politics local
politics so that is the agenda and that
is still at play that is still at play
your textbooks are still distorted your
textbooks still have enormous omissions
of your own history and world history
and the way they teach history and they
teach Science and Mathematics or
anything is is it it hurts my brain
physically when I see these
textbooks these people who write who
formulate these
textbooks I wonder what IQ they have or
maybe they are very intelligent but they
have a nefarious
agenda so there is a crying need to
reform the education
system but it's not happening
and these five years it's not going to
happen so yeah I've kind of given up
hope on
that now siia says what do you think was
the basis on which Indians were divided
into among many casts four casts four
not many cast four by the British to
divide and Rule and how can we Indians
how can we as Indians solve this problem
the problem is that it is not in our
hands anymore see India has never had
cast four casts India has has had the
Verna and jati system which is a system
system of classification and division of
labor India is a 10,000 year old plus
Society obviously there's going to be
division of labor and social
classification and all that it happens
in any functioning Society so we had
tremendous numbers of tremendous
quantities of uh veras and jatis I mean
four veras in in tremendous quantity of
jatis and the British could not
understand this they could not wrap
their little puny little Minds around
that so they over simp ified everything
by creating forecasts and force fitting
people into these
forecasts that's what is they have done
and today we are Tau that it is a social
evil that is is the legacy of our
ancestors now what can we as Indians do
today to solve the problem we can do
nothing the government has to solve this
problem but the
government um well the system benefits
the politicians who are in power today
so why will they solve this why will the
change
anything think about it the politicians
who are in power today they came to
power through the system so why will
they change the system
why the system has benefited them that's
why they're in power today why will they
change it so I don't see it being solved
but what would you what would you do to
solve the problem so you can only solve
the problem if you are in power in the
government you as common people can do
nothing about it it's very simple to
solve this first of all
delete all references to
cast in your government and education
certificates and birth certificates why
do you need to mention cast if cast is
not important then delete all references
to cast from your birth certificate from
your government
documents and from your education
education
documents delete everything end of story
there's no official cast anymore that's
number
one secondly
give reservations if necessary on the
basis of economic status not cast these
two things will immediately end the
problem but no politician will have
the let's say the guts to do that no
politician will do that because it may
be political
suicide but somebody has to take the bll
by the horns who is that leader going to
be that is going to be the next great
leader of the country right now we have
no great leaders or great enough leaders
this is a gigantic problem that needs to
be solved and the solution is
straightforward but difficult it'll take
a leader of exceptional fortitude to do
this and right now we don't have such
leaders okay rodra sarar asks a question
the question is did ancient Indians have
any common language that could connect
the whole subcontinent really sir or did
they have so many Regional languages as
we have now we've always had Regional
languages a subcontinent sized Nation
enormous gigantic Nation Indians we see
this map of India and we think it's a
small nation it's an enormous Nation
India and historical India was even
larger than that our border Northwestern
border was the border with Turkmenistan
sorry
Tajikistan in the 12th
century India's Northwestern border was
the border between today's border
between Afghanistan and
Tajikistan okay so historically India
was even larger than what it is today so
obviously you will have lots of local
languages just like
today but we always had one common
language that unified the subcontinent
civilization it's the world's oldest
known language it's
Sanskrit that was our civilization
language and it was spoken in all
civilized parts of the world in the old
days before the Turks and the Europeans
destroyed
India so even today in Indonesia they
still have Sanskrit names megawati
sukarnoputri and they
have mixed names also so the strangest
names you will see
what Muhammad Vishnu that's we'll see
over there but anyway the point is we
always had that civilizational language
srit and the fact that we don't have a
civilizational language today indicates
that we have given up the status of
civilization India today today's India
is not a civilization today's India is a
mere nation state so those politicians
who like to TomTom that we are the
world's oldest civilization if you want
India to be the world's oldest
civilization to still have that status
you need to bring back
Sanskrit slogans will change nothing
slogans will do thing they won't even
get you elected these slogans unless you
do some action so yeah so Sanskrit was a
language Malik sad says it's a hard fact
we know
that an average Indian is not
disciplined and polite on the ground
level resulting in poor waste management
and other things my question is is it
not was it not the same case in China
two decades ago how did they change from
this and how did they teach their people
discipline then how can we do that in
India that is an excellent question look
first of all every nation has a set of
standards and what standards are these
you see the standards of a Nation are
generally set by the top 0.1% of the
population top is in the highest
achieving people the people who really
make the nation work you know what
Mustafa kimal atat used to say he he
didn't say this but he had the
greatest of he he had a great belief
atat tur in the greatness of his Nation
turkey but he despised the average
ordinary Turkish
person he had a very low regard for the
average Turk but he had the highest
belief in the nation and you will say it
doesn't make any
sense it makes sense
it is the top 0.1% of people who
actually run a country and who set the
standards for the whole country to
follow and the greatness of a country
depends on the greatness of that 0.1% of
the population so those of you who want
to really make a difference you need to
strive to be among the 0.1% of the
population the genuine movers and
Achievers of a Nation so that's first of
all number one so the average person is
going to have have low standards you go
to Any Nation the average person will
have lower standards than perhaps the
standards of the best in the nation now
secondly you are right most Indians are
indisciplined they will litter on the
streets some of them will spit on the
streets they are not well behaved
impolite
Etc um and all that yes but isn't it
curious that the same Indians the moment
they go to a first world country their
entire behavior and attitude changes and
they are generally the most low abiding
demographic in the west Indians and the
highest achieving demographic in the
West on
average why is it so so does it mean
that the average
Indian is to blame for the situation
that is not the
case when Singapore became an
independent nation it had abysmal
standards it was a third world country
people had they had the same attitudes
as the as people in small towns in India
today so how did Singapore become become
a first world country in just one
generation 20 years through iron
discipline and enforcement of that
discipline through harsh
means Singapore's leader was a
benevolent dict dictator Mr lewu and he
imposed a harsh regime of discipline in
Singapore heavy back back breaking fines
for a simple thing like spitting on the
street or not flushing a toilet seat or
or not flushing a toilet extremely harsh
punishments for the smallest of
infractions and over a few years
everybody straightened out everybody
became people with higher standards so
that's how you do it you do it by
enforcing first of all setting down the
rules of behavior and then enforcing
those rules of behaviors
rigidly and and and meeting out harsh
punishments but not horrible punishments
harsh punishments to those who break the
rules you need to have
enforcement that's how very quickly
people will change their behavior it's
about incentives and dis incentives
that's it human psychology basic
pavlovian psychology almost and the
Chinese they have been trying to emulate
Singapore now I think D shopping said
that if if I was running just one city
Shanghai then I could replicate what
lean you did in Singapore but
unfortunately he was ruling a nation of
1 point three billion people at the time
so it's taking time obviously but the
Chinese have also tried to replicate the
Singapore model and they obviously have
very strict discipline very harsh
punishments and all that so it's working
there also so my point is you don't need
to abuse human rights in terms of your
of the harsh of of your harshness of
your punishments but you need to have
consistent predictable punishment if
somebody breaks the law so if you break
the law you should be certain that I'm
going to be punished now and if the
certainty of punishment is there then
you will not break the law and that's
how you make people behave and very
quickly people adapt and they all become
law abiding people and they all become
people with the highest Civic SS that
what that's what needs to happen so the
low standards emanate from the
government of India I'm not talking
about the government at the top in Delhi
I'm talking about your local
municipalities and District corporations
and all that these are the people these
are the administrations that should be
enforcing these rules and and raising
the standards but they don't do that I'm
sure there are places in India where
actually you have very high standards
maybe higher than Singapore I'm sure
there are places like that so I'm not
seeing all Municipal corporations and
all district administrations are like
that some of them may be better than New
York I'm sure but many of them have
rather you know low standards that's
what I that's what I mean
rodit sarar says did ancient India
establish any InterContinental trade
routes like the Silk Road which land and
SE routs did ancient Indians used to
trade with other countries okay let's go
to the map of course you had these
things India used to trade 2,000 years
ago okay let's go back older than that
3,000 4,000 5,000 years ago India was
trading with uh
Mesopotamia uh and we know that because
we have indust sarasti Hindu Ira Indian
ports and settlements in Oman in eastern
Iran Etc we have found Saraswati Hindu
seals in the Mesopotamia region between
the tigis and Euphrates rivers so there
is ample evidence that India was trading
with Mesopotamia four 5,000 years before
today so the trade route was via the uh
Gulf of Oman the Persian Gulf the
straight of Hormuz over here then India
was trading with with Egypt about 4,000
years ago at least
uh and we have evidence of that as well
so that's 4,000 years ago then we know
that India was trading with
Rome 2,000 years ago with they have
found statues of Indian Indian Ivory
carved gods and goddesses in uh I
believe Pompei or herculanum and other
other parts of Italy they found Indian
coins in various parts of Italy which
was ruled by Rome and they found lots
and lots of Roman coins Etc in various
parts of India in temples and other
archaeological sites they found Roman
aoras etc etc etc in India so India was
trading with Rome 2,000 or so years ago
that is a whole long route trade route
and Indians have settled in Eastern
Africa for centuries if not thousands of
years the eastern part of Africa is
deeply deeply influenced by Indian
culture in ways that are still visible
to today in the cuisine in in in the
kind of uh clothing that they wear and
even in the genetics even in the
genetics of their cattle and all that
and obviously India has been trading
with Eastern Asia for centuries for
about 3,000 years the people of Kalinga
had have been trading with swabi which
is Thailand and Southeast Asia for about
3,000 years they used to cross the the
ocean in ships and vasod dama when he
came to when he reached the Cape of Good
Hope and he wanted to find a way to
India uh he met Indians in Eastern
Africa and that's how he was able to
come to India with their help and he
thought that he had the world's biggest
ship but then he saw an Indian ship
which was about three times the size of
his ship so that that's
how that's how good Indian ships were so
that is inbrief the kind of inter
International InterContinental trade
routes that India had and I'm sure we
had
other trade routes that we may not even
be aware of
today okay why whyu says two questions
unlike unlike southeast Asia why
couldn't Hinduism culturally influence
or gain followers in Central Asia and
Western Asia what are the reasons behind
this secondly why don't we find any
Indian cultural or religious presence in
Central Asia I'm not talking about the
Buddhist influence is there any Hindu
presence that predates the Buddhist
influence okay Central Asia what is
Central Asia yes let's take a look at
the map okay we are in the Indian Ocean
region let's go northwards so Central
Asia is essentially present day sang The
tarim Basin River all the way up to
let's say the Caucasus region and the
Central Asian step which is kazakistan
ETC all the way up to Eastern Ukraine
that is what you could say is Central
Asia okay that's the region uh that weo
weo is referring to now what's the
deal here's the
deal there were indianized kingdoms all
across Central Asia for thousands of
years before Buddhism was even born when
what's the beginning of Buddhism the
birth of Gotham Buddha right his his his
life his life his lifetime which is
about two and a half roughly thousand
years before
today um so before that there was no
Buddhism there was only Hinduism and
jism so so
the latest tankar is bhagan mahavir who
was kind of a contemporary of the Buddha
and there were tankar before him also it
is said and there are Buddhas before
Buddha also but as far as we are
concerned we can say that the bud that
Buddhism began with the birth of Buddha
or his lifetime about two and a half
thousand years before today before that
there was no Buddhism there was only
Hinduism various forms of Hinduism
various schools of thoughts and all
that so these old indianized Kingdoms in
Central Asia dating back thousands of
years were all Hindu kingdoms or at
least initially originally the people
who migrated there were Hindus and then
over centuries they may have diverged in
their Lifestyles and and eventually
Indians called them Bas which means that
they no longer follow the Vic Customs
properly maybe they only semi follow the
Vic Customs or maybe they abandoned
entirely um so you had a Hindu influence
all across Central Asia then what
happened is the question why do we see
nothing of that
today well if you go to kyrgistan
kazakistan turkistan you will see almost
no Buddhist relics also over there maybe
one or two ruined sters here or there
maybe in turkistan something is there a
little bit here and there but not much
Afghanistan gandar was was part of India
until 800 years ago so that you will
find over
there but turkistan you may see one or
two archaeological sites and not much
more beyond that what happened to all
the bud let's talk about the Buddhist
Tas where are those where have they
gone and before the Buddhist tupas you
would have had Hindu temples where did
those
Go I mean is it so hard to answer so
first of all let's talk about let me go
to the map again it let's talk about
something less controversial to start
off with
Armenia so today if you go to
azaran okay to Baku there is a sun temp
there is a fire temple there which is
used by Hindus as well as Zoro austrians
because Zoroastrianism came from
Hinduism so very similar religions you
can say so that fire temple is used by
zoroastrians as well as Hindus in Baku
aeran now Armenia historically was much
larger and aeran did not even exist at a
point in
time so Armenia is said to be the
world's first Christian Nation and one
of their kings about 2,000 or so years
ago uh mandated that everybody has to
convert to
Christianity before Armenia became a
Christian Nation it was was a
zoroastrian and Hindu
Nation okay
Armenia today the Turks you know what
they call the Armenians they call them
Indians so Armenia used to be a
zoroastrian and Hindu nation and there
were Hindu temples in Armenia and about
2,000 years ago these temples were
destroyed Hindu temples were destroyed
and churches were built on top of them
of these Hindu temples and about a
century or so ago those those churches
were destroyed in mosques were built on
top of them so now that you see the
pattern is it so hard to understand
where all the Hindu and Buddhist relics
went in Central Asia that's how it
typically
goes so everything was destroyed and new
religious structures abrahamic religious
structures came up on top of
them that's what happened that's why you
will see no Hindu temples and almost no
Buddhist uh temples stoas Etc in Central
Asia and uh one of the things that
chingis Khan did the great Mongol
conqueror chingis Khan when he conquered
quasm which is in Central Asia and also
Iran he destroyed some of these mosques
and built Buddhist temples on top of
them so he knew what had been going on
there so that's what happened so you had
Hindu influence actually at a point in
time the whole of Central Asia was Hindu
later there was Zoras influence later
there was Buddhist influence and
eventually there was Islamic influence
going back about about a thousand years
only before today so until a thousand
years ago it was all Hindu Buddhist zor
asrian today they will see no evidence
almost no evidence of the old culture
that's how thoroughly everything has
been wiped
out Amit kubar says India had great
scientists and mathematicians and the
renowned n the university given our
historical achievement in the military
might we had in terms of size at the
time why didn't we develop Advanced
military technology to gain an edge over
over Islamic Invaders especially
considering the references to powerful
weapons like the brahmastra in our
history okay forget about the brahmastra
we had a great culture great
civilization great universities lot of
mathematics tremendous architecture
geometry calculus infinite series
astronomy everything we had right what
about the Egyptians they could build the
greatest monuments in monaster the
pyramids they had tremendous scientific
achievements
advancements they had great pharaohs
great Kings they had good technology
what happened to them they allowed the
first the Persians and then the Greeks
to overrun them and then the Arabs what
happened they also had great Advanced
Weaponry what about the Greeks the
Greeks had Sparta we are Sparta they had
the great Spartan Warriors the they had
the
phanes they had those ramming galys they
had such great technology what happened
to the
Greeks the Greeks are also said to be
great mathematicians and so on what
happened so were the Egyptians what
about South America the Aztecs the Incas
they also had great technology they had
a calendar system that went back
thousands of years they also had huge
pyramids they also had science and all
that what happened to them why did they
fall to the rag tag Barbarian Europeans
what happened
so understand my friends from this
pattern that I've shown you that great
culture great civilizational great
civilization great scientific
advancements all that is not something
that will prevent your culture and your
nation from being
destroyed you need the right kind of
leadership if you're scientists are
great if your universities are the best
in the world and your culture is the
best most advanc and richest culture in
the world but your leader is preoccupied
with culture and and having fun and is
neglecting the Armed
Forces then no matter how great you are
you're going to be wiped out by a b by a
bunch of desert Warriors who have no
culture or or snow Warriors who have no
culture
okay that's the
deal so so that's as simple as that so
either so so one thing is yeah the main
thing is leadership and you may have
great leaders but if those leaders if
that leader is not in power in control
of the whole country and if you have
multiple kingdoms and it's all
fragmented and not politically United
then once again you're going to fall
victim to a barbarian enemy who is
focused only on one thing
Warfare so technology culture all that
doesn't matter you need for a nation
India you need a centralized power uh
system an imperial system
essentially and you need a proper focus
on National Defense on on the
military and on and on keeping an eye on
the threats outside of your
country that's what needs to happen and
that's how so when the Turks invaded
India India was not politically United
like it was during the Moria Empire the
kusan Empire the Gupta Empire and so on
India was at the time going through that
period of political fragmentation so you
had lots of Kingdoms smaller kingdoms
and no one great leader in the
country and also we were too civilized
we used to fight we had rules for
fighting we would not fight at night we
would not stab in running enemy a
fleeing enemy in the back we would be
merciful and so on our objective was to
be brave and chivalrous and cultured and
the objective of the enemy was to
win so someone where we so it's a
question of the quality of leadership
and nothing more ruthless
leadership Anand Anand says how does
excavation takes place do archaeologists
know they will find specific things
beforehand if they dig there or do they
find things by accident for example
excavation of ancient sites excavation
of Temple Idols even excavation of
potteries from backyards of homes how do
they manage to pinpoint all these sites
good question archaeologists usually do
not randomly go and start digging
anywhere they don't do that they dig on
what is called promising sites so there
is some historical context for example
to these to the to the place where
they're going to dig for example in
somea all across India you will find
these
Mounds these Mounds are ancient sites
that generally Are soil covering an
ancient Temple or a stupa or something
so when you see these Mounds that arise
out of nowhere you typically know that
there something there which is
archaeologically
interesting and then you obviously have
sites that have this historical
reputation of having been having of
having been historically very
significant so we have the oral history
because our records have been burned in
the in the destruction of the University
so we have this oral records and oral
lore so because of these things and then
you can do underwater sonar surveys you
can do leadar mapping of under
underground artifact and so on and so
forth so you can do certain things
before you start to dig somewhere but
generally you only dig when you know
that this site is a promising site
because of the factors that are just
outlined some of the factors are the
ones that are outlined and there may be
other factors as well when it comes to
this so that's how we do it you don't
randomly start digging just about
anywhere even though that could also
work in India because India is so old
but generally you start because because
of the because of the uh scarcity of
resources money funding Etc you only dig
where you are pretty certain to find
something good so you look at a site
based on you identify sites that you
will dig based on how promising they are
based on the already known factors
that's how we do
it chandani prya says what should our
country's strategy to have good and
friendly relations with Russia and China
and also some European countries which
are friendly towards us B be friends
with everybody that's it win-win
cooperation uh mutually beneficial
relationship trade economics strategic
Affairs everything should be mutually
beneficial and we should try to be
friends with everybody that should be
our straightforward strategy next as a
30 year-old Indian citizen what can I
teach my children so that they can be
responsible for their actions and their
actions towards our nation look there's
so much you can teach and it's very
difficult but the most important thing I
would say is teach your children our
culture teach them their mother tongue
they should know how to read and write
in their mother tongue and teach them
their culture expose them to our
cultural heritage in whatever ways read
the Raman Mahabharat bhagwat Gita
whatever to them or whatever it is that
your family you know tradition is and
make them familiar with the with their
mother tongue whatever mother tongue you
have and if possible srit also and I
know it's easier said than done today
children are already you know they're
already shouldering enormous burdens of
education so much they have to study so
much homework so much extracurricular
curricular nonsense and mo 80 or 90% of
what they are being forced to study is
going to be of no use to them in the
future so it is a pointless worthless
useless education system but children
have to go through this and to put this
on top of that is going to be an extra
burden so it's easier said than done but
that's what you should do if you can
teach your children our culture Our
Heritage expose them to this from an
earlier age from an early age and that
will make them better better citizens
overall okay done with the questions
from the comments now let's take some
questions from the live chat so my dear
friends I'll take about 10 minutes or
so um off your live chat questions so go
ahead please ask me questions in the
live chat let's take this one by tipu
Master years later what's going on at
and what's deployed at the farore and ID
air bases in Tajikistan given their
location they seem extremely well placed
to develop for pining let's take take a
look at Ai and
farore so um where is AI Airbase where
is farore Air
Base they are air bases in I believe
usbekistan or Tajikistan I think
Tajikistan okay let's see farore air
base so Zoom there you go so it is in
Tajikistan on the border with
Afghanistan and this is the farore air
base now let's go to the map view and
see if we can discern the air
base where is
it
um not that visible is
it I remember seeing the air base in the
past uh it's got to be somewhere
here that's strange how is
it
farore let's
see okay where could this be I have seen
that in the past has it been erased of
the map okay so looks like I'm not able
to locate it right now it should be
visible at the 1 kilometer or so range
somewhere here and I remember it was
along the border with Afghanistan I
remember
that okay let's take a look at i i a y n
i so where is that okay this one is more
visible so this is I air base is it near
dasan
Bay so let's zoom in so this one is very
visible do we have any air assets over
here these
are clearly military helicopters
these are clearly a Soviet vintage
aircraft migs of some kind Etc are these
tajic uh assets or are they Indian
assets not very sure let's see what we
have
here uh these are not combat aircraft
these are aircraft of some other card
kind so this air base is clearly
operational
I when it comes to the far core Air Base
it I'm not sure what's going on there so
farore is on the border with
Afghanistan the other one is much
further into Tajikistan so that's the
deal I I can show you only what's
visible from here I don't know what's
happening because I'm not part of the
government and I'm not privy to uh
privileged
information they are obviously very well
placed for let's say pins sering so if
you look here it's a you can reach
Pakistan from there in a matter of
minutes if you are on a super sonic
fighter plane and that's why these air
bases are important for India so that's
what I can say I don't know really what
this latest status is but yeah that's
where they
are
uh okay let's take some other questions
maybe two three more
questions only Jim says this is promode
from Kerala why don't you meet Mr Modi
and share your suggestions about reform
our education system we'll support you
and do your respons do our
responsibility to to the nation thank
you so much I really appreciate it the
thing is Mr Modi is a person who is an
incredible
demand everyone wants to meet him and he
doesn't have the time to meet everybody
and who am I who am I I'm I'm just some
guy right so maybe in the future if I'm
fortunate I may meet Mr Modi I I have
the privilege to meet him but
uh yeah that's the
deal so
that's what I can say uh he's not
someone who is easy to meet he's the top
leader in the nation his time is
extremely valuable he has so much work
to do his time is very regimented every
day is planned out with very very very
important things and it's that's why
it's very very hard to to meet him so I
was there in rashap ban last weekend I
was there at Mr modi's inauguration and
the in the swearing in ceremony of the
Modi 3.0 cabinet ministers and in
Ministers of State
and yeah I was there but meeting him
maybe it may happen someday if I'm if
I'm fortunate in the future and if I do
meet him someday I will certainly will
express my opinion as to what needs to
happen but I really appreciate uh your
support really does I I really I really
does we does appreciate your supports we
does yes indeed Yes
precious Yes
precious okay
Anisha says in Maharashtra in
Maharashtra a famous baloi person lives
parit baloi okay all
right
um Sami Jen says is Mak a good leader
he's not a bad leader he's an okay
leader I would say uh he is doing the
best he can in the in the context of the
geopolitical situation that's prevalent
in the world right now that France is
not a fully Sovereign Nation it's part
of the it's part of the European Union
it's also part of NATO so much of its
sovereignty is gone by being part of two
organizations that take away some of
your sovereignty and overall the US it
it R it it rules Europe Western Europe
so in the context of all of that that
situation whatever he can do he's doing
for his country from that perspective
he's a reasonably good leader but not a
great leader by any means but a good
leader for sure not a bad
leader okay
what else do we have you have questions
you ask me now good questions
yes
um Naman Jen says could the H promotion
of Hindi be strategically better in the
1940s to unite India linguistically
while retaining the native language of
every state or could it have been
another language look if you want a
language that is universally understood
and accepted it's not Hindi it's
Sanskrit today they have engineered the
nation in such a manner that it's now
Hindi but if you were in the 1940s
Sanskrit was a much better option but in
the past 70 years they've made Hindi the
whole
thing Hindi is just well it's it's a
language that's spoken in some parts of
India native to a small part of India
and it has got lots of dialects so it
was by no means the right choice for
being the official or quazi official
language of India it
is the hindustani language it's Hindi
uru so on the correct the right the only
right choice is is sanskrit but
M
um goami says are children in the west
taught the correct history that shapes
them even in the west they not taught
the correct history history the way you
teach history is a important tool by
which you can can indoctrinate people
and shape their world viiew so history
that's why it's so important that's why
history is so important the way you
teach history one example is Germany
I've spoken about this like three four
years ago I think on one of my earlier
earliest live streams I think the top
between 1 to 50 episode number so in
Germany there was a battle I think in
around around 10 ad 10 ad and it was a
battle between various Germanic
tribes they fought together against the
Roman Empire and their leader the leader
of the Germanic tribes was a guy who had
lived some part of his childhood as a
hostage to Rome so he was familiar with
Roman culture Etc his name was
armenius in Latin and Herman in German
so this guy he led this Coalition of
Germanic Tri tries in the battle of the
torberg forest and decimated three
entire Roman
Legions the Varian regions Legions varus
was their their commander varus and when
this happened when Vos realized what the
hell has happened he did the natural
thing and he fell on his sword and
committed suicide so the I think the
year 2010 plus or minus one or two years
was the 2,000th anniversary of the
battle of tberg forest in Germany and
almost no one in Germany celebrated this
why is that because they not taught
their history because God forbid the
Germans become nationalists
again when the Americans think about
German nationalism they so they see
those Hugo Boss uniforms and those
marching boats Germany must never
allowed to be rise never be allowed to
rise again so don't teach them their
correct history so even in the west they
don't teach the right history good good
very good point youve raised here
gotami jitu chatri says China says that
it will build 10, j20 fighter planes
generation five fighter planes by 2035
while yeah while see quantity has a
quality of its own especially when the
qu quality is good so even if you have a
MIG 21 class fighter I'm not saying the
Mig 21 itself which is obsolete very old
but something of that class of that
caliber and you have 2 of those it's a
formidable challenge for any enemy so
quantity has a quality of its own that's
what Joseph Salin said and he was right
the Chinese are doing the right thing
what about us how many 36
raffals 36 rals and maybe 36 more in the
next 10 years what are we
doing we need to spend more of our GDP
our budget on the military it is
imperative we do that and we need to
boost the number of warheads we have
those Warheads the spice spice Warheads
we need a thousand of those anyway
that's where we are
now Dr J shanka says modi's Italy visit
yes Mr Modi has I think he's still there
is he back I'm not sure but he was in in
Itali U on the invitation of Madame
milone uh for the G20 Summit sorry the
G7 Summit so whenever the G G7 Summit
happens it used to be the G8 but theyve
expelled Russia from that so it's it's a
G7 now and Mr Modi was there and he was
kind of he took center stage in the in
the group photograph and so on and he
met with various leaders and the memes
are are
out I think Madame milone enjoys the
memes why not it's good to see a
politician with a with a sense of humor
so yeah so they are kind of feeding the
memes in India and uh so overall it was
a good visit visit he met mudo he met Mr
M Mr Modi met with
old sorry President
Biden he met Madame Mone he met
everybody that was of any importance and
I think it's good uh to touch Bays with
the major world
leaders so it's interesting that India
is is usually invited to the G7 but
Russia is not and China is not that
tells you certain things okay that tell
you tell you certain
things oh okay pret says how to exactly
read books effectively the philosophy or
methodology to read books is very simple
open a book and before you start reading
a book you should have some idea of what
you want from this book why am I reading
this book number one you should know
secondly what am I hoping for in this
book and third you should allow yourself
to forget everything if the book is not
valuable if you don't get what you what
you seek from the book so my method My
Philosophy is very simple I I take a new
book I don't have to finish the whole
book I may put it aside after chapter or
two if it's not interesting or I may
skim through the chapters and see if
there is something in there that is of
any use to me and maybe there's
something maybe 10% of of the book is
good or or relevant to me I will read
that and I'll leave the rest behind I'll
leave the rest aside and even if I read
an entire book I'm perfectly okay with
forgetting everything if it doesn't
interest me so that way I am sure that I
will remember what I find interesting
and that's typically the stuff that I
think is important so that's how I do it
that's how I've always done I've read
thousands of books I'm sure I've
forgotten 80 90% of what I've read but
some of that has gone in some of that
little bit small brain you see so that's
how you read books that's how I read
books and maybe that will help you also
okay I think I am going to wrap it up
now so thank you once again to everybody
for for all your questions for
participating as usual uh apologies to
those of you whose questions I could not
take I see thousands of questions coming
in every week I can only take a handful
so sorry to those of you there are lots
of good questions that I can't take
every week so so apologies to those of
you whose questions I could not take but
I will take as many questions in the
future as possible and we will keep on
doing the ask show so thank you so much
once again and I will see you very soon
next week in the next episode of asit
until then take care and keep raising
your standards thank you bye good day
good night see you soon